<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BrewingNerd</title>
    <description>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 19:46:01 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 19:46:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.3.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The wild world of cleaning and sanitation</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are two types of brewers, those who have infected their beer and those who haven’t noticed it yet.&lt;br /&gt;
-A Wise Homebrewer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An infected beer is an insidious and disheartening problem.  When I was a new brewer, I brewed the same beer three times in a row.  I kept detailed notes and was focusing on my repeatability.  To my surprise the third batch tasted horrendous.  It had a thick, stringy, pellicle sitting on top.  I followed the exact same steps, I cleaned my equipment the exact same way.  What I didn’t realize is that my process was flawed.  My lack of understanding provided a window of opportunity for these unwanted microbes to take hold.  Why didn’t it happen on the other two batches? Sheer luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contamination in the brewing process is not just a homebrewer’s problem.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://revbrew.com/whats-new/detail/ale-product-withdrawal-10-17-2016&quot;&gt;Foreign&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.denverpost.com/2016/09/12/left-hand-brewing-recalls-milk-stout-nitro/&quot;&gt;yeasts&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chicagobusiness.com/article/20160715/BLOGS09/160719858&quot;&gt;bacterial infections&lt;/a&gt; affect even the big boys.  The Brewing Science Institute even provides a nice &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brewingscience.com/PDF/BSI_brewers_lab_handbook.pdf&quot;&gt;handbook&lt;/a&gt; for QA staff.  The goal they present is to have less than or equal to 10 colony forming units.  As we’ve seen from these recent recalls, this is not a simple problem.  While homebrewers may not have the benefit of a decked out QA lab with microscopes, slides, incubators and petri dishes, we also don’t have challenge of properly cleaning and sanitizing massive fermenters, hundreds of feet of piping, and managing huge vats of caustic and acid chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing a sanitary process for your homebrewing is not as difficult.  Although experienced homebrewers usually have their preferences, there are many commercial options available at local homebrew stores.   I woud caution a new brewer to be wary of what comes with some homebrew kits.  I’ve seen the documentation that comes with some of these kits that run fast and loose with these very specific terms and provide just downright wrong information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this series we take a deeper look into what cleaning and sanitization mean and how to get the best results during your brew day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Part 1: Introduction (You’re Here)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Part 2: Common Brewing Contaminants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Part 3: Cleaning Vs. Sanitizing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Part 4: Best Practices and Tips and Tricks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/29/the-wild-world-of-cleaning-and-sanitation.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/10/29/the-wild-world-of-cleaning-and-sanitation.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
