<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BrewingNerd</title>
    <description>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 11:58:53 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 11:58:53 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.3.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Brewing clean: cleaning vs. sanitizing (part 3)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We know that minimizing the introduction of microbial contaminants is imperative to ensuring a quality final product.  To do this, we clean and we sanitize.  While they are often introduced hand in hand, they are two quite separate things.  Cleaning is the process used to remove foreign matter from a surface.  On the pro-brewer scale, this is usually accomplished largely by using clean in place (CIP) techniques.  High pressure streams of acid and caustic washes provide an automated solution for many large vessels.  The remainder is usually cleaned &lt;em&gt;out of place&lt;/em&gt; with some elbow grease. On the homebrew scale, there are just too many requirements to effectively operate a CIP system.  Maintaining a sanitary environment is a wholly separate process and system.  While a sanitary environment requires proper cleaning, it also goes beyond that.  It includes such aspects as preventing grain dust floating in the air, the use of aseptic techniques, and keeping pests at bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cleaning-agents&quot;&gt;Cleaning Agents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;warm-water-and-mechanical-cleaning&quot;&gt;Warm Water and Mechanical Cleaning&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this may seem like a given, using warm water and a good brush or pad will clean out an astonishing amount of dirt and grime on brewing surfaces.  By cleaning off surfaces as you brew, the dirt and grime doesn’t have time to harden up.  With a bit of scrubbing, most foreign matter can be cleaned out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;household-detergent&quot;&gt;Household Detergent&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standard household dish detergent does its job in the homebrew environment.  The surfactant in detergent works well when dealing with oily and organic matter.  Try to seek out a fragrant and dye free brand and rinse well following cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;sodium-percarbonate-oxiclean&quot;&gt;Sodium Percarbonate (Oxiclean)&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sodium Percarbonate (Na&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;CO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;•3 H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) is the active ingredient in number of commercial cleaners such as OxiClean and OxiBoost.  This oxidizing cleanser is commonly used on homebrewing equipment.  It is commonly used to remove the adhesive left on recycled beer bottles.  A few hour soak in a warm OxiClean bath makes short work of the gummy residue.  A good rinse with hot water following cleaning is necessary to remove any remaining cleanser. Seek out the fragrant and dye free versions (i.e. OxiClean Free).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;pbw&quot;&gt;P.B.W.&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Powdered Brewery Wash (P.B.W.) is a buffered alkaline detergent combination of Sodium Metasillicate (Na&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;SiO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;) and Sodium Percarbonate.  Due to the Sodium Metasillicate, it has increased buffering abilities in hard-water environments.  PBW is used in the same manner as Oxiclean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;tri-sodium-phosphate-tsp&quot;&gt;Tri-Sodium Phosphate (TSP)&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re unlikely to see much of true TSP on the shelves anymore.  Just a few short years ago it was ubiquitous in cleaning products but its use was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eutrophication&quot;&gt;wreaking havoc on lakes and rivers&lt;/a&gt;.  Many of the TSP branded cleaners no longer have any actual TSP in them anymore.  Lets not screw up our lakes and rivers any more than we already have, there are other options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;bar-keepers-friend&quot;&gt;Bar Keeper’s Friend&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 134 year old cleaning product, Bar Keeper’s Friend, is well known for cleaning stainless steel.  It’s active ingredient, Oxalic acid (C&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;) works well to remove rust, burnt on grime, and beer stone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sanitizing-agents&quot;&gt;Sanitizing Agents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;bleach&quot;&gt;Bleach&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The old standby; Bleach. Regular old household bleach (Sodium Hypochlorite - NaClO) has been used for millennia.   A solution of 1 tablespoon per gallon is an effective sanitizing agent given 20 minutes of contact time.  A complete rinse is required.  It can also be used as a cleaning agent.  For those who don’t use bleach often, a reminder:  Do not mix bleach with ammonia based cleaners.  This will produce Nitrogen Trichloride (NCl&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;), a compound that causes severe lung injury.   Don’t leave the bleach solution in contact with metals for a extended period of time as the solution will cause corrosion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;iodine-iodophor&quot;&gt;Iodine (Iodophor)&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most popular Iodine based sanitizer, Iodophor, is widely used in the food industry.  At the manufacturer recommended concentration, the solution sanitizes in ten minutes.  While there is some anecdotal evidence for the contact time being as little as one minute, ten minutes is still recommended by the manufacturer.  While it is quite effective as a sanitizer, it will not function as a cleanser.  All surfaces must be free of any foreign matter.  Iodophor is a no-rinse sanitizer, but be forewarned, it will stain plastics.  The resulting brown hue is just cosmetic.  Homebrewers with an iodine allergy should avoid Iodophor and choose an alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;star-san&quot;&gt;Star San&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Star San is possibly the most popular no-rinse sanitizer in homebrewing.  One ounce of the Star San concentrate diluted in 5 gallons of water will produce a solution where the active ingredient, Dodecylbenzenesulfonic acid (C&lt;sub&gt;18&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;29&lt;/sub&gt;NaO&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;S), will have a 300ppm concentration.  The contact time of Star San is 1 to 2 minutes and the sanitizing solution can be sprayed on, or the surface can be submerged in the solution.  The manufacturer specifically states to not rinse the surface following application of star san.  You can keep a bucket of Star San around between brew days as long as the pH remains below 3 (pH test strips are handy for this).  Use of RO or distilled water will lengthen the time a batch will last.  Star San, when agitated, produces a large volume of fluffy foam.  This foam will sanitize the surface it’s touching.  Don’t fear the foam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;a-word-of-caution&quot;&gt;A word of caution&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still a few homebrew kits and old Geocities websites saying that some cleansers on the market (c-brite, one-step) are sanitizers.  While these cleansers have some sanitizing action due to their peroxide generation, their efficacy is either unproven or poor.  It’s best to use these as cleansers and then use a true sanitizing agent.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/11/02/Brewing-Clean-Cleaning-vs.-Sanitizing-(Part-3).html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/11/02/Brewing-Clean-Cleaning-vs.-Sanitizing-(Part-3).html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Brewing clean: common brewing contaminants (part 2)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Brewing, in an overly simplistic sense, is the creation of growth media for the single celled organism of choice.  It just so happens that we have developed a taste for the resulting waste liquid.  Our goal as brewers is to control the living organisms that are present in our beer to only the ones we want.  Understanding what common contaminants are, where they come from, and what issues they present assist the brewer in developing a system that limits the probability of contamination and infection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;microbial-contaminants&quot;&gt;Microbial contaminants&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The microbial contaminants we cover here fall into three broad categories: yeasts, gram-positive bacteria, and gram-negative bacteria.  While it may be counterintuitive that yeast is included as a category, wild or unintended yeasts that make their way into the wort can affect the final product.  The same goes for bacteria.  Many styles of beer rely on bacteria to provide it’s signature taste or mouthfeel.  While in these styles the aforementioned microbes are not contaminants, if they are unintentionally present in a beer it is considered a flaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yeasts&quot;&gt;Yeasts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The single celled eukaryotes known as yeasts are nearly omnipresent in the environment.  While the term yeast is often used to describe either brewing or baking yeast strains, there exist a plethora of non-brewing strains.  The Saccharomyces genus contains the top cropping (&lt;em&gt;S. cerevisiae&lt;/em&gt;) and bottom cropping (&lt;em&gt;S. pastorianus&lt;/em&gt;) strains of brewers yeast.  These yeast strains &lt;em&gt;ingest&lt;/em&gt; sugar and &lt;em&gt;expel&lt;/em&gt; ethanol and CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.   There are significant differentiation among strains which result in different fermentation characteristics and flavors.  The remaining yeast strains cover many different genera and have widely different effect on wort.  It also contains some other well known yeasts such as Brettanomyces, wich is commonly used for the &lt;em&gt;farmhouse funk&lt;/em&gt; flavor it can impart on the beer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bacteria&quot;&gt;Bacteria&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bacteria are generally split into two groups gram-negative and gram-positive. This designation is based on their reaction to crystal violet dye.  The staining technique, developed in 1884 by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans_Christian_Gram&quot;&gt;Hans Christian Gram&lt;/a&gt;, is quick and simple way to identify the presence of peptidoglycan in the cell wall of these bacteria.  This differentiation is helpful in organizing and classifying different bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;gram-positive-bacteria&quot;&gt;Gram-positive Bacteria&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two common gram-positive bacteria present in some styles of beer are Lactobacillus and Pediococcus.  These bugs both produce lactic acid as opposed to a yeast’s production of ethanol.  This leads to the lowering of the beer’s pH. This mechanism of action is sought after in sour beer styles.  In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://byo.com/light-ale/item/889-how-to-make-a-sour-mash-techniques&quot;&gt;sour mash and sour worting techniques&lt;/a&gt;, it is common to use malted grain as a source of Lactobacillus delbruckii.  Care must be taken to create an environment that is favorable to L. delbruckii and hostile to other microbes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pediococcus is another beer spoiling microbe that, when controlled and introduced intentionally, can provide an interesting final beer.  Pediococcus strains also generate lactic acid and, like lactobacillus, can form a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.milkthefunk.com/wiki/Pellicle&quot;&gt;pellicle&lt;/a&gt; on the top of a beer.  A significant impact that Pediococcus can impart on a beer is a described “ropiness” or slick mouthfeel.  To offset this, intentionally inoculated beers are usually paired with Brettanomyces which is able to break the offending exopolysaccharides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining gram-positive bacteria are generally seen as beer spoiling contaminants.  Many of these bacterium are pellicle forming and may not reach a taste or observation threshold until after packaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;gram-negative-bacteria&quot;&gt;Gram-negative Bacteria&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gram-negative grouping of bacteria encompass the remaining commonly found bacteria.  They have widely different effects on finished beer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enterobacteriaceae are a wide grouping of gram-negative bacteria.  Generally speaking, these microbes are alcohol and pH sensitive.  An infection of one these bacterium typically occurs prior to the completion of fermentation.  The commonly described off flavors caused by this group is &lt;em&gt;baby dipers&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;barnyard&lt;/em&gt;.  Some Enteric bacteria can produce dimethyl sulfide and diacetyl beer spoiling compounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another commonly found group of gram-negative bacteria are the microbes that produce acetic acid.  The most notable, Acetobacter, is commonly used to produce vinegar.   Acetobacter, and the lesser known Gluconobacter, are widely present in the environment and convert ethanol into acetic acid.  While not often a issue in properly packaged beer, it is quite common in dirty or improperly cleaned draft equipment and taps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;going-forward&quot;&gt;Going Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have a basic understanding of what microbial contaminants are common in the brewing environment, we can continue on to understanding what products and systems can keep these microbes at bay.  &lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Head on over to Part 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/11/01/Brewing-Clean-Common-Brewing-Contaminants-(Part-2).html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/11/01/Brewing-Clean-Common-Brewing-Contaminants-(Part-2).html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Brewing clean: the wild world of cleaning and sanitation (part 1)</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are two types of brewers, those who have infected their beer and those who haven’t noticed it yet.&lt;br /&gt;
-A Wise Homebrewer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An infected beer is an insidious and disheartening problem.  When I was a new brewer, I brewed the same beer three times in a row.  I kept detailed notes and was focusing on my repeatability.  To my surprise the third batch tasted horrendous.  It had a thick, stringy, pellicle sitting on top.  I followed the exact same steps, I cleaned my equipment the exact same way.  What I didn’t realize is that my process was flawed.  My lack of understanding provided a window of opportunity for these unwanted microbes to take hold.  Why didn’t it happen on the other two batches? Sheer luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contamination in the brewing process is not just a homebrewer’s problem.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://revbrew.com/whats-new/detail/ale-product-withdrawal-10-17-2016&quot;&gt;Foreign&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.denverpost.com/2016/09/12/left-hand-brewing-recalls-milk-stout-nitro/&quot;&gt;yeasts&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chicagobusiness.com/article/20160715/BLOGS09/160719858&quot;&gt;bacterial infections&lt;/a&gt; affect even the big boys.  The Brewing Science Institute even provides a nice &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brewingscience.com/PDF/BSI_brewers_lab_handbook.pdf&quot;&gt;handbook&lt;/a&gt; for QA staff.  The goal they present is to have less than or equal to 10 colony forming units.  As we’ve seen from these recent recalls, this is not a simple problem.  While homebrewers may not have the benefit of a decked out QA lab with microscopes, slides, incubators and petri dishes, we also don’t have challenge of properly cleaning and sanitizing massive fermenters, hundreds of feet of piping, and managing huge vats of caustic and acid chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing a sanitary process for your homebrewing is not as difficult.  Although experienced homebrewers usually have their preferences, there are many commercial options available at local homebrew stores.   I woud caution a new brewer to be wary of what comes with some homebrew kits.  I’ve seen the documentation that comes with some of these kits that run fast and loose with these very specific terms and provide just downright wrong information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this series we take a deeper look into what cleaning and sanitization mean and how to get the best results during your brew day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Part 1: Introduction (You’re Here)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Part 2: Common Brewing Contaminants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot;&gt;Part 3: Cleaning Vs. Sanitizing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/29/Brewing-Clean-The-Wild-World-of-Cleaning-and-Sanitation-(Part-1).html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/10/29/Brewing-Clean-The-Wild-World-of-Cleaning-and-Sanitation-(Part-1).html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An argument for homebrewing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We homebrewers are a quixotic bunch.  Some of us may spend hundreds (if not thousands) of dollars on equipment.  Some of us are slow to learn our lessons and are forced to dump gallons of undrinkable liquid down the drain.  Some of us structure our free time to be able to spend hours in blazing heat or frigid cold while hunched over the brewing system left to just hope that the final product meets our lofty goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why do it?  Craft beer has exploded.  Great beer is available in far-flung corners of the country.  Craft Breweries are opening at an exponential rate.  So why do we homebrew?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not claim to speak for all homebrewers, but I am friends with quite a few.  Homebrewers want to make a hight quality product.  Some of us just want the satisfaction that we are able to make a product that most of our neighbors and friends just go out and buy.  There appears to be a significant crossover with people who like to do things themselves (just look at the DIY community).  When I jumped into the hobby a decade ago, the homebrewing market was small but plentiful.  Today, there are cottage manufacturers growing into market players, homebrewing startups hanging up the proverbial shingle, and exponential growth in the market size.  While the DIY route is no longer an necessity, there is pride in not only making great beer but also in designing and building a brewing system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are on the fence about starting to homebrew, know that there are a plethora of resources available to you these days.  Homebrewing blogs (like this one) are popping up like weeds.  There are homebrew clubs across the country and across the world filled with knowledgable, kind, and generous homebrewers who will help in any way possible.  Personally, I give back because far wiser and far more intelligent homebrewers have given me the knowledge to get where I am today.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/10/26/An-Argument-For-Homebrewing.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/10/26/An-Argument-For-Homebrewing.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
